The latest limited edition pin is here.
Now available on the Kurz Gesagt shop.
You will never leave the solar system.
Nobody alive today will, and maybe no
human ever.
Locked in by an invisible barrier,
impossible to overcome for carbon-based
animals like us. And not just us, there
may [music] be millions of alien
civilizations in the universe, none of
them ever able to venture into [music]
deep space in a meaningful way.
Okay, but how can this be?
We've made countless videos imagining
how the exploration of the galaxy and
[music] beyond should just be a question
of time, sort of mandatory for
civilizations at a certain point. But
there's [music] a catch. We're pushing
up against fundamental physics. What is
this barrier made of dust and
nothingness? And why is it so hard to
overcome?
You don't understand how large space is.
We don't either.
Conceptualizing [music] the size of
space is impossible for our ape brains
that evolved to understand distances
like right here and over the next hill.
Space is [music] so absurdly huge that
we just check out and just hear very
far. Very far and
>> [music]
>> a million times very far feels the same.
But it's not.
To help our brains, let's start with
what makes us cross distances, speed.
The fastest a human ever traveled in
space were astronauts at 40,000 km an
hour returning from the moon [music] in
1969.
Not bad, but way too slow.
The fastest thing humans have ever built
by far is the Parker Solar Probe,
[music] which at this moment uses a
physics cheat code hurling around the
gravity well of Venus accelerating to
get closer to the sun. After 7 years of
doing this, the probe is shooting
through space at a breathtaking [music]
635,000
km an hour, fast enough to go around the
world in 4 minutes or to cover the
distance from Earth to the moon in 36.
So, let's pretend we had a spaceship
that fast with a human crew ready to
explore the universe.
Current rockets would need [music] 7 to
10 months to reach Mars, but our new
spaceship covers the distance in just 2
weeks. Pretty good.
The next stop is Pluto, which we'll
reach after [music] about a year. Okay,
much longer, but still okay. It only
takes 2 more years to pass the
heliopause and one more to pass Voyager
2, which traveled over 50 years to get
this far.
Great.
The next stop is the end of the Oort
Cloud, the true [music] edge of the
solar system, where open space begins.
We reach it in
2,500
years.
Oh.
Oh, no.
Not only did we travel for the amount of
time it took to get from the founding of
the Roman Republic to the present day,
there's nothing out here.
This is the invisible barrier, the
barrier of nothingness that might trap
us in the solar system forever.
Space tends to be like that.
There is a place that's very far away,
but with human ingenuity and billions of
dollars, [music] we can get there. Then
you zoom out one more time and all hope
leaves your body. And the problem is
that we've barely started zooming out.
Why don't we just go faster?
Well, we don't know of a non-magic way
to travel faster than light, teleport,
or freeze people.
>> [music]
>> So, no warp drive for now. But, things
like a propulsion system that uses
nuclear fusion or antimatter, powerful
enough to reach a substantial [music]
fraction of the speed of light, are in
the realm of the physically possible.
Ignoring the [music] technical details
and various problems that these energy
sources have, we'll be very optimistic
and make the reasonable assumption that
we can get a spaceship to fly at around
20% [music] the speed of light, which is
extremely fast, 60,000 km [music] per
second, 216 million km per hour. Fast
enough to reach [music] the edge of the
solar system in just 3.5 days and the
outer edge of the Oort Cloud in 8 years.
Alpha Centauri, the [music] closest star
system to our own, in 20 years.
We can work with that. There's only one
small [music] problem. We don't have
internet. Wait. What?
Just kidding. But our sponsor Saily can
help you with that problem while
traveling. Saily is the eSIM [music]
service app from the creators of Nord
VPN. You can choose from a wide range of
affordable eSIM [music] plans for over
200 destinations, so you'll never be
without an internet connection while
traveling. Just download [music] the
app, pick a data plan, use the code
Kurzgesagt for a 15% discount on your
first data package, and install [music]
the eSIM in advance. It'll activate
automatically when you arrive, and you
can start browsing right away. You can
also use Saily to feel like a local.
[music] It now comes with an app-based
phone number for voice calls and SMS
that stays the same everywhere.
>> [music]
>> Perfect for local apps, shops, and
travel companions, and to keep your real
number private. With just one app
download, you've solved [music] your
internet problem while traveling once
and for all, saving time and expensive
roaming fees. Download Saily and use the
code Kurzgesagt at checkout, or go to
saily.com/kurzgesagt.
All you have to do is [music] pick your
next destination. We'll go back to
solving our trickier travel problems.
Everything [music] should be sorted out
now, right? Well, there's only one small
issue. Space hates you.
The barrier of dust.
Unfortunately, we'll run into a few
obstacles on the way.
Literally. Because while space is very
empty,
>> [music]
>> it's not actually empty.
There are energetic particles, gas,
dust, and things bigger than dust. As a
lot of unhappy people experience every
[music] day, if you're going really fast
and smash into something, you have a
huge problem. And at 20% the speed of
light, [music] this is true even if the
thing you're smashing into is just an
atom.
An individual iron atom that hits your
spaceship at this speed [music] has
enough energy to carve a damage track
tenths of a millimeter deep.
Over time, [music] its hull would be
riddled with microscopic bullet holes,
which is not great.
Of course, our engineers knew this and
created [music] a shield for our ship, a
sort of protective cell that absorbs or
at least slows down [music] most
molecules we smash into.
And while this makes the journey much
safer, there are things floating [music]
around in space that are larger than
atoms. Running into a single grain of
dust at 20% the speed of light is like
running into a grenade, causing a tiny
detonation as the dust explosively
evaporates, grinding away our protective
shield. But you can [music] also hit
something bigger than a grain of dust,
like a small rock the size of a golf
ball. Hitting that at 20% the speed of
light
>> [music]
>> releases more than double the energy of
the nuclear bomb that was dropped over
Hiroshima.
We'll not even talk about anything
larger.
Atoms, dust, and pebbles are dangerous
enough.
We might have reached our natural speed
limit here. Beside the fact that we
don't have a good idea how we could
possibly fly any faster, all of the
damaging effects of hitting stuff
floating around in the void get much
worse, fast.
Having said all that, it's probably fair
to assume that with enough shielding,
our spaceship should be able to survive
traveling through space
>> [music]
>> at roughly 20% the speed of light long
enough to get to at least nearby stars
in a reasonable amount of time.
Only one more issue to overcome.
Almost everything in space that's close
is super lame.
The first proper target outside the
solar system is the Alpha Centauri
system, which is roughly 10,000 years
with our original slow, more realistic
ship, but only 20 years with our super
fast a ship.
So, let's cram a few unlucky humans into
a tiny box for 20 years and send them on
their way and assume they somehow make
it without murdering each other.
Four years after their arrival, their
message reaches Earth. People around the
globe gather together and hold their
breath, eager to listen to it.
We arrived. Alpha Centauri and its
planets are very [music] pretty up
close. Unfortunately, they're all super
deadly and uninhabitable. But, we're
doing extremely cool astrophysics and
are [music] learning a lot, which is
pretty exciting. We're getting kind of
tired of freeze-dried food and
desperately need new shows to watch,
though. Not sure what we were thinking
coming here.
The thing about space is that almost all
close destinations, if close means
something different from what it usually
means, are pretty lame.
Not from a scientific perspective, of
course. It would be an absolute dream to
have [music] the privilege to set foot
on foreign planets and marvel at the
wonders of our universe.
But, if 20% [music] of the speed of
light might be our speed limit and we
give humans a realistic travel time of,
say, 40 years, [music] we could reach
things that are up to eight light-years
away.
None of the targets remotely within this
range within [music] a human lifetime
may be worth traveling dozens of years
in a tiny box through one of the
deadliest environments [music]
imaginable. Our solar system is a bit
unlucky in that regard. We're in a
relatively empty pocket of the galaxy.
This might change [music] in a few
million years as we move through the
galaxy, and there might be small,
localized star-spanning [music]
civilizations. We discussed this in
another video.
Let's say that we [music] could go much
further, to any of the stars within our
stellar neighborhood, a sphere about 25
light-years in diameter.
0.02%
of the Milky Way, by the way.
This tiny bubble [music] is currently
inhabited by 34 stars and six brown
dwarfs.
Only three stars in our neighborhood are
similar to the sun.
But, one of them is actually the sun,
and another one is Alpha Centauri A.
The other stars close to us are mostly
red dwarfs with planets that vary from
deadly [music] to super deadly.
There are a few planets in the habitable
zones of their stars where water can be
liquid,
>> [music]
>> but Mars is also in the habitable zone
of the Sun and it's really bad. Even the
planets that we think look most like
Earth, like GJ 1061D, come with no
guarantees. [music]
Imagine traveling your entire life and
then arriving at a Mars. [music]
What a brutal letdown that would be.
There are a few stars that would be
interesting targets and may have actual
habitable planets, planets with oceans
and atmospheres that are breathable,
which probably [music] would mean that
they have some form of microbial life,
if not more.
It would be extremely interesting and
definitely worth it to check them
[music] out. But they could be dozens,
if not thousands, of light-years away.
Which means journeys of hundreds or
thousands of years, even at a large
fraction of the speed of light.
Of course, it is maybe feasible that a
future humanity that is technologically
way more advanced than us and very
motivated could find solutions.
Maybe they've solved biological aging
and a travel time of a few hundred years
doesn't seem that [music] bad to them.
Maybe they could send AI spaceships with
embryos or some version of that into
space. They'd probably have way more
advanced telescopes [music] to make sure
they don't choose star systems that are
deadly and empty, but it's still hard to
imagine without real science fiction
technology how they could build and
sustain a connected civilization.
Conclusion.
The longer you think about deep space,
the less it makes sense.
The distances are too vast. There's a
deadly speed limit and even if we could
solve these issues, almost all
destinations even remotely reachable may
not be worth the trip. Space is the
greatest challenge humanity will ever
face. Right now, we're just not equipped
or able to solve it.
>> [music]
>> Rockets, computers, and even nuclear
fusion reactors are hopelessly
underpowered. We need technology that's
overwhelmingly transformative. Something
as wild to us as flying to the moon
would have been to a hunter-gatherer.
Will we ever get there? We genuinely
don't know.
But it is good to remind yourself of
something.
There are few things that make you look
dumber than predicting the future of
technology. In 1903, The New York Times
published an editorial "Flying Machines
Which Do Not Fly" that confidently
predicted it [music] would take humans 1
to 10 million years to achieve powered
flight. 69 days later, the first
successful flight happened. 66 years
later, humans landed on the moon. So, we
really hope this video will seem as dumb
as this article in 100 years.
And there's another option entirely.
Maybe our thinking about all of this is
just completely wrong. Maybe the future
is not [music] out there, but deep down.
But we'll explore that in another video.
The latest limited edition pin is here,
continuing the Cosmic Time collection.
Predicting the future is really hard,
but this device offers you a rare
glimpse into the end of the universe.
[music]
Spoiler, one by one all the stars will
die until everything is swallowed by
darkness. [music]
Wear this animated lenticular pin as a
reminder that you exist right now in a
brief and extraordinary moment in time
[music] when the universe is still
filled with stars and light, and there's
so much left to discover. You're exactly
where you belong in cosmic time and the
universe.
Only 10,000 Vanishing Stars [music] pins
exist, and each one is individually
numbered. Add it to your collection or
start a new one while supplies last. And
while humanity may still be confined
[music] to a tiny corner of the cosmos,
we've already achieved some remarkable
things. To celebrate these milestones,
[music]
we we our Cosmic Milestones poster
collection featuring the first moon
landing, the Mars rover Curiosity, and
the Wilson [music] Observatory all
enhanced with shimmering foil details.
Get your favorite or better all of them
and create a gallery wall that will
inspire you [music] every day and remind
you of what humanity is capable of. Head
over to our shop. We've put together a
few deals for you. Get your special
piece of Kurzgesagt and the cosmos now.
You want to listen to the beautiful
soundtrack without my annoying voice?
Hmm, well it's up to you. Just select
the audio track interlingua down here
and watch the video again as a music
video.